<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<csd-standard xmlns="https://www.metanorma.org/ns/csd">
<bibdata type="standard">
<title language="en" format="text/plain">Report on CalConnect Test Event and Developers Forum XLI, January 29-31, 2018</title>
<docidentifier type="csd">CC/A 1802:2018</docidentifier>
<docnumber>1802</docnumber>
<date type="published">
<on>2018-03-02</on>
</date>
<contributor>
<role type="author"/>
<organization>
<name>CalConnect</name>
</organization>
</contributor>
<contributor>
<role type="publisher"/>
<organization>
<name>CalConnect</name>
</organization>
</contributor>
<edition>1</edition>
<version>
<revision-date>2018-03-02</revision-date>
</version>
<language>en</language>
<script>Latn</script>
<status>
<stage>published</stage>
</status>
<copyright>
<from>2018</from>
<owner>
<organization>
<name>CalConnect</name>
</organization>
</owner>
</copyright>
<ext>
<doctype>administrative</doctype>
<editorialgroup>
<technical-committee>IOPTEST</technical-committee>
</editorialgroup>
</ext>
</bibdata>
<boilerplate>
  <copyright-statement>
    <clause>
      <p id="_949746da-910e-47f5-a278-500b7593c27c">© 2018 The Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium, Inc. </p>
    </clause>
  </copyright-statement>

  

  <legal-statement>
    <clause>
      <p id="_57b1ec19-191c-4995-a63e-86d39665c350">All rights reserved. Unless otherwise specified, no part of this
        publication may be reproduced or utilized otherwise in any form or by any
        means, electronic or mechanical, including photocopying, or posting on the
        internet or an intranet, without prior written permission. Permission can
        be requested from the address below.  </p>
    </clause>
  </legal-statement>

  <feedback-statement>
    <clause>
      <p id="boilerplate-name">The Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium, Inc.</p>
      <p id="boilerplate-address">4390 Chaffin Lane<br/>
        McKinleyville<br/>
        California 95519<br/>
        United States of America<br/>
        <br/>
        <link target="mailto:copyright@calconnect.org">copyright@calconnect.org</link><br/>
        <link target="www.calconnect.org">www.calconnect.org</link>
      </p>
    </clause>
  </feedback-statement>
</boilerplate>

<preface><foreword id="_3ebcab0b-fbda-4671-bc25-8a897ef16c48" obligation="informative"><title>Foreword</title><p id="_e470dc7a-beb8-49c1-aa6f-1f3b4556a5bf">The Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium (“CalConnect”) is a global non-profit
organization with the aim to facilitate interoperability of technologies across
user-centric systems and applications.</p>
<p id="_eb1499a9-4f81-4f16-a555-a3ba45e1debd">CalConnect works closely with liaison partners including international
organizations such as ISO, OASIS and M3AAWG.</p>
<p id="_84bd8ee2-cec4-4aad-a741-1f717a2ed242">The procedures used to develop this document and those intended for its further
maintenance are described in the CalConnect Directives.</p>
<p id="_c1edd260-c101-4f6b-b3d2-db9ba6d9360b">In particular the different approval criteria needed for the different types of
ISO documents should be noted. This document was drafted in accordance with the
editorial rules of the CalConnect Directives.</p>
<p id="_59baefee-09d3-45d5-8f78-9de986ac8a5b">Attention is drawn to the possibility that some of the elements of this
document may be the subject of patent rights. CalConnect shall not be held responsible
for identifying any or all such patent rights. Details of any patent rights
identified during the development of the document will be in the Introduction
and/or on the CalConnect list of patent declarations received (see
www.calconnect.com/patents).</p>
<p id="_61e64cab-24eb-4df9-99df-900a37a19040">Any trade name used in this document is information given for the convenience
of users and does not constitute an endorsement.</p>
<p id="_d66f488b-927a-4e35-ad75-c69ff24e3757">This document was prepared by Technical Committee <em>IOPTEST</em>.</p></foreword></preface><sections>
<clause id="_report" obligation="normative"><title>Report</title><p id="_934894aa-5c0b-42cb-8754-f15fb408c238">The event was hosted by Oath in Sunnyvale, California, January 29-31, 2018</p>
<p id="_f6e78823-84f7-410f-9fcc-a40e7f664f9d">In attendance for this interoperability event and developers forum were:</p>
<ul id="_005dc04f-4796-4308-9f24-b44f74e7cde0">
<li>
<p id="_d33468ad-584d-46d0-8595-839918f0cfa9">Mike Douglass Spherical Cow Group — managing the event</p>
</li>
<li>
<p id="_f3d15b35-ac75-4f74-ba1b-c1ad420aeacb">Ken Murchison for Fastmail</p>
</li>
<li>
<p id="_53c3bf4a-ebdd-4f04-934d-5f34d45c503c">Thomas Schäfer for 1&amp;1</p>
</li>
<li>
<p id="_836ce0a9-ff3b-451d-a243-913c7ba83b50">Greg Solovyev for Zimbra</p>
</li>
<li>
<p id="_af507b62-78f1-40c0-8598-a5407762de2c">Peter Tam for Ribose</p>
</li>
<li>
<p id="_13b730e1-071c-4a14-81d3-b06a522229fd">Richard Brigham and Anjj Kumar Tweari for Oath</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p id="_96fea3b6-4a9d-4cb3-a6b9-4b3ec06f8cfc">Despite the small attendance we managed to cover a number of topics.</p>
<p id="_bdde7ddc-3d60-44cf-96d7-f5f402996897">There was some work being done with <tt>ical4j</tt> as we continue to try to move forward to a version
based on the latest from Ben Fortuna. Some members have heavily modified older versions but
are getting closer. We intend to create a clone with some or all of the members’ changes which
can be used as a staging point for pushing them up to Ben.</p>
<p id="_4a4d5bb8-33cb-470e-8c53-dbf096adbcd7">There was some discussion on the work that is going on with vCard or its replacement. There
are still questions on how to represent all the desired groups of information. It seems the
discussions helped clarify some points.</p>
<p id="_1d7020ea-90c8-43dc-b1bf-9de43305a443">There was more work trying to get the CalDAV tester running. Anuj from Oath got Darwin and
the tester running together in record time and then proceeded to run tests against their server.</p>
<p id="_55ce1f92-4d39-4f42-bca5-0f884b1a74d8">There was more work on updating the developers guide.</p>
<p id="_e180034b-f1cd-4ae1-8bda-d65fc5162ac2">In addition we were working on getting vPoll running again as there was to be a demonstration
in the main conference following.</p>
<p id="_cdc4be98-3e5c-4749-aba5-aca8518ef7ee">We should remind potential attendees that the developers forum and test event is as much
about detailed discussions on points of implementation as it is about testing. It provides an
opportunity to discuss those small details. If you do have something to test or develop then
come early and get advice on the best path to take.</p></clause></sections>
</csd-standard>
